Guide to the Cornell Rankhandi project records, 1953-1984.
Cornell Rankhandi project records, 1953-1984
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Cornell Rankhandi project records, 1953-1984.
14-25-2787
Cornell University. Dept. of Anthropology.
48.9 cubic ft.
Photographs, motion picture film, audiotapes, maps, subject files, index cards, field notes
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Field notes, subject files, cross index cards, surveys, photographs, movie films, audiotapes, maps, census data, and other documentary and research material of the Cornell Rankhandi Project. The project used the control Muslim village of Jhabiran in its study, and embraced the disciplines of anthropology, religion, sociology, political science, economics, linguistics, child psychology, history, and social psychology. Team members include Michael Mahar, Pauline Kolenda, Allan Atwell, John Gompers, John T. Hitchcock (Project Director), Robert T. Smith, Morris E. Opler, and Pat Hitchcock.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
The Cornell Rankhandi Project was a sociological and anthropological study of the North India village of Rankhandi (Khalapur) undertaken in conjunction with Lucknow University of India, with the additional participation of the Ford Foundation.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Field notes, subject files, cross index cards, surveys, photographs, movie films, audiotapes, maps, census data, and other documentary and research material of the Cornell Rankhandi Project. The project used the control Muslim village of Jhabiran in its study, and embraced the disciplines of anthropology, religion, sociology, political science, economics, linguistics, child psychology, history, and social psychology. Team members include Michael Mahar, Pauline Kolenda, Allan Atwell, John Gompers, John T. Hitchcock (Project Director), Robert T. Smith, Morris E. Opler, and Pat Hitchcock.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Cornell University.; Atwell, Allan.; Gompers, John.; Hitchcock, John T.; Hitchcock, Pat.; Kolenda, Pauline.; Mahar, J. Michael; Opler, Morris E., 1907-; Smith, R. T.(Robert T.); Ford Foundation.; Lucknow University.
Subjects:
Anthropology--India.; Sociology--India.; Political science--India.; Economics--India.
Places:
Rankhandi (India).; Khalapur (India).; Jhabiran (India).; India--Language.; India--Religion.; India--Economic conditions.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Audio tapes.; Motion pictures.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Movie film
(16mm) by Pat Hitchcock. Includes outtakes. Village of Rankhandi (also known as Khaalaapur). Morris E. Opler, from the Ford Foundation. North Indian village prior to development. US/India Joint University Venture (Lucknow and Cornell)1953-56. Disciplines of study include anthropology, sociology, political science, economics, linguistics (John Gompers), child psychology, history, social psychology. John T. Hitchcock, Project Director. Robert J. Smith.
Series II. Photographic
Includes colored slides, black and white negatives in isinglass slips, 3x5 drawers. Years of study: 1954, 1984 (1968, 1978, 1984 - Smithsonian)
Series III. Field notes
HRAF format, typed cross index cards.
Series IV. Black and white prints
HRAF code, indexed with key
Series V. Allan Atwell files
Contemporary art of India.
Series VI. Maps
Regulation government maps, specialized maps (eg. every house, tree, well in a village, population 5000)
Series VII. Phonodiscs
Language records, 78 rpm, archaic vocabulary, Basis of Gompers' introductory Hindi
Series VIII. Surveys
Crop production and other surveys
Series IX. Jhabiran files
Control village (Muslim) most others are Hindi. HRAF coded, includes photographs.
Series X. Census material
Most comprehensive village study ever. All documented, statistics of health.
Series XI.Audiotapes
Village dialect, village music
CONTAINER LIST
- Jhabiran (Box 1-8)
- Photographs (mounted)
  - Jhabiran photos & Ref. Info. 13, 23-58a (Box 9)
  - Photos 34-36, 40-41, 53c, 54, 57-58 (Box 10)
  - Photos 66b-67, 7576, 78-79a (Box 11)
  - Photos 58-59, 65-65b, 65g, 66-66b, 75,79-79b, 85, 87-88b (Box 12)
  - Photos 44, 48 51-53b, 58e (Box 13)
  - Photos 65f-65k, 66a (Box 14)
  - Photos 59, 62, 65-65e, 88c, 89 (Box 15)
  - Photos 79b, 85, 87, 88-88b (Box 16)
  - Photos 10, 13-13c, 22-24b (Box 17)
  - Photos 25-34 (Box 18)
  - Photos 88c-89 (Box 19)
  - Photos 12,25-30 (Box 20)
  - Photos 1-9, 14-42 (Box 21)
- Index Cards (Box 22-32)
- Movie Films (Box 33-35)
  Three audio cassettes of music labeled Reels 12-16, Reels 17-20, and Reels 21-24 from Box 34 have been digitized.
- Audio Tapes (Box 36)
- Slides (Box 37-42)
- Miscellaneous Files, Photographs, slides (Box 43-44)
- Maps (Box 45-48)
- Additional Census Records (Box 49)
- Additional field notes and slides
  - Ideas 1955 (Box 50, Folder 1)
  - Slides: Baba (neg. f/slide set c) and two unidentified (Box 50, Folder 2)
  - Riter: b/w negs 1954 (Box 50, Folder 3)
  - Minturn 1976 (Box 50, Folder 4)
  - Amaawas 1955 (Box 50, Folder 5)
  - Notes 1955-1956 (Box 50, Folder 6)
  - Notes re: other 1955-1956 (Box 50, Folder 7)
  - Gourdhan 1954-1956 (Box 50, Folder 8)
  - Bhaiya Dooj 1955 (Box 50, Folder 9)
  - Besant Panchmii 1955-1956 (Box 50, Folder 10)
  - Davali 1954-1955 (Box 50, Folder 11)
  - Hoi - Data 1955 (Box 50, Folder 12)
  - Solono 1955-1956 (Box 50, Folder 13)
  - Calendrical interpretation 1955 (Box 50, Folder 14)
  - Holi 1954-1956 (Box 50, Folder 15)
  - Ritual designs 1955 (Box 50, Folder 16)
  - Naumii 1955 (Box 50, Folder 17)
  - Cal. Rite - Misc. - seen by Bruce 1955 1962 (Box 50, Folder 18)
  - Cal. Rites f/S.T. 1955 (Box 50, Folder 19)
  - Karva Chauth 1954-1955 1979-1980 (Box 50, Folder 20)
  - Karvaa Chuth 1955 (Box 50, Folder 21)
  - Paintaa 1955 (Box 50, Folder 22)
  - Sat Naraayan Purnima Bhats Eclipse 1955 (Box 50, Folder 23)
  - Shiv Chaudas (Box 50, Folder 24)
  - Shiuratrii (Box 50, Folder 25)
  - Sakat Puja 1955-1956 (Box 50, Folder 26)
  - Athanaumii & fasts 1955 (Box 50, Folder 27)
  - Aamal Eekaadashii 1956 (Box 50, Folder 28)
  - Kanagats 1955 (Box 50, Folder 29)
  - Ritual paintings in R. Int. guides 1956 (Box 50, Folder 30)
  - Giaas 1954-1956 (Box 50, Folder 31)
  - Misc. - Int. Guides, etc. 1955-1956 (Box 50, Folder 32)
  - Solono 1955 (Box 50, Folder 33)
  - Worshipping at Mela 1955 (Box 50, Folder 34)
  - Sugar Cane Planting Wall Design 1955 (Box 50, Folder 35)
  - Teej Sauan 1955 (Box 50, Folder 36)
  - AsaaRh 1955 (Box 50, Folder 37)
  - Sauan 1955 (Box 50, Folder 38)
  - Puran Maashii 1955 (Box 50, Folder 39)
  - Deshera in Jaith 1955 (Box 50, Folder 40)
  - Janamaastamii 1955 (Box 50, Folder 41)
  - Misc. Cal. Rites 1954-1956 (Box 50, Folder 42)
  - Phulanin Dooj 1955-1956 (Box 50, Folder 43)
  - Chaudas of Asooj 1955 (Box 50, Folder 44)
  - Org. Cere. - RMM - 1 of 3 folder 1955-1956 (Box 50, Folder 45)
  - Hoi to Sanghi, prints p/ Greg 195- (Box 50, Folder 46)
  - Sanghi Gouardhan 195- (Box 50, Folder 47)
  - 01 Unclassified 1954-1956 (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - 02 Daily Log 1953-1954 (Box 51, Folder 2)
  - 10 Orientation 1955 (Box 51, Folder 3)
  - 102 Maps 1955 (Box 51, Folder 4)
  - 11 Bibliography 1954-1955 (Box 51, Folder 5)
  - 12 Methodology 1954-1955 (Box 51, Folder 6)
  - 13 Geography 1955-1956 (Box 51, Folder 7)
  - 15 Behavior Processes and Personality 1954-1956 (Box 51, Folder 8)
  - 16 Demography 1954-1956 (Box 51, Folder 9)
  - 17 Historical and Cultural Change 1954-1956 (Box 51, Folder 10)
  - 18 Total Culture 1953-1955 (Box 51, Folder 11)
  - 19 Language 1955-1956 (Box 51, Folder 12)
  - 20 Communication 1955 (Box 51, Folder 13)
  - 21 Records 1955 (Box 51, Folder 14)
  - 22 Food Quest 1955 (Box 51, Folder 15)
  - 23 Animal Husbandry 1954-1956 (Box 51, Folder 16)
  - 24 Agriculture 1954-1956 (Box 51, Folder 17)
  - 24A Agriculture Interview, Answers to IG-32-I: Harvest 1956 (Box 51, Folder 18)
  - 24B Agriculture Land Records (S. N. Singh) 1956 (Box 51, Folder 19-20)
  - 24C Agriculture Land Use Tables and Figures 195- (Box 51, Folder 21-22)
  - 25 Food Processing 1954-1955 (Box 51, Folder 23)
  - 26 Food Consumption 1954-1955 (Box 51, Folder 24)
  - 27 Drink, Drugs, and Indulgence 1954-1956 (Box 51, Folder 25)
  - 28 Leather, Textiles, and Fabrics 1955-1956 (Box 51, Folder 26)
  - 29 Clothing 1954-1956 (Box 51, Folder 27)
  - 30 Adornment 1954-1956 (Box 51, Folder 28)
  - 31 Exploitative Activities 1955 (Box 51, Folder 29)
  - 32 Processing of Basic Materials 1953-1955 (Box 51, Folder 30)
  - 33 Building and Construction 1954-1956 (Box 51, Folder 31)
  - 34 Structures 1954-2956 (Box 51, Folder 32)
  - 35 Equipment and Maintenance of Buildings 1954-1956 (Box 51, Folder 33)
  - 36 Settlements 1955 (Box 51, Folder 34)
  - 37 Energy and Power 1955 (Box 51, Folder 35)
  - 40 Machines 1954 (Box 51, Folder 36)
  - 41 Tools and Appliances 1955-1956 (Box 51, Folder 37)
  - 42 Property 1954-1956 (Box 51, Folder 38)
  - 43 Exchange 1954-1956 (Box 51, Folder 39)
  - 44 Marketing 1955-1956 (Box 51, Folder 40)
  - 45 Finance 1956 (Box 51, Folder 41)
  - 46 Labor (1-139) 1954-1956 (Box 51, Folder 42)
  - 46 Labor(140-267) 1954-1956 (Box 51, Folder 43)
  - 47 Business and Industrial Organization 19 (Box 51, Folder 44)
  - 48 Travel and Transportation 1954-1956 (Box 51, Folder 45)
  - 49 Land Transport 1955-1956 (Box 51, Folder 46)
  - 51 living Standards and Routines 1954-1955 (Box 51, Folder 47)
  - 52 Recreation 1954-1956 (Box 51, Folder 48)
  - 53 Fine Arts (53-41) 1954-1956 (Box 51, Folder 49)
  - 537 Mundiaa Chamaar Songs (MM) 1955-1956 (Box 51, Folder 50)
  - 54 Entertainment 1954-1956 (Box 51, Folder 51)
  - 55 Individuation and Mobility 1954-1956 (Box 51, Folder 52)
  - 56 Social Stratification 1954-1956 (Box 52, Folder 1)
  - 56 Social Stratification (89-303) 1954-1956 (Box 52, Folder 2)
  - 56 Social Stratification 1954-1956 (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - 57 Interpersonal Relations 1954-1956 (Box 52, Folder 4-5)
  - 58 Marriage (1-190) 1954-1956 (Box 52, Folder 6)
  - 58 Marriages: Three Chamar Marriages (Mike Mahar) 1955-1956 (Box 52, Folder 7)
  - 58 Marriage (191-388) 1954-1956 (Box 52, Folder 8)
  - 59 Family 1953-1956 (Box 52, Folder 9)
  - 613.1 Khandan Study (MM) 1955-1956 (Box 52, Folder 10-13)
  - 60 Kinship 1954-1956 (Box 52, Folder 14)
  - 61 Kin Groups 1954-1956 (Box 52, Folder 15)
  - 62 Community 1954-1956 (Box 52, Folder 16)
  - 65 Government Activities (1-99) 1954-1956 (Box 52, Folder 17)
  - 65 Government Activities (100-199) 1955-1956 (Box 52, Folder 18)
  - 65 Government Activities (200-299) 1954-1956 (Box 52, Folder 19)
  - 65 Government Activities (300-388) 1954-1956 (Box 52, Folder 20)
  - 65 Government Activities (389) 1955-1956 (Box 52, Folder 21)
  - 65 Government Activities (390-411) 1954-1955 (Box 52, Folder 22)
  - 65 Government Activities (412-489) 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 1)
  - 65 Government Activities (490-503) 1953-1956 (Box 53, Folder 2)
  - 65 Government Activities (504-533) 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 3)
  - 65 Government Activities (534-543) 1953-1955 (Box 53, Folder 4)
  - 65 Government Activities (544-556) 1951-1955 (Box 53, Folder 5)
  - 66 Politicalk Behavior 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 6)
  - 67 Law 1953-1955 (Box 53, Folder 7)
  - 68 Offenses and Sanctions 1955-1956 (Box 53, Folder 8)
  - 69 Justice 1953-1955 (Box 53, Folder 9)
  - 70 Armed Forces 1954-1955 (Box 53, Folder 10)
  - 73 Social Problems 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 11)
  - 74 Health and Welfare 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 12)
  - 75 Sickness (1-145) 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 13)
  - 75 Sickness (146-248) 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 14)
  - 76 Death 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 15)
  - 77 Religious Beliefs (1-173) 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 16)
  - 77 Religious Beliefs (174-391) 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 17)
  - 78 Religious Practices 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 18)
  - 79 Ecclestical Organization (1-66) 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 19)
  - 79 Ecclestical Organization (67-126) 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 20)
  - 79 Ecclestical Organization (167-213) 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 21)
  - 80 Numbers and Measures 1954-1955 (Box 53, Folder 22)
  - 81 Exact Knowledge 1955 (Box 53, Folder 23)
  - 82 Ideas About Nature and Man 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 24)
  - 83 Sex 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 25)
  - 84 Reproduction 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 26)
  - 85 Infancy and Childhood 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 27)
  - 86 Socialization 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 28)
  - 86A LM's Mother, Father and Child Interviews: Morbidity, Fasts 1954-1955 (Box 53, Folder 29)
  - 86B LM's Observations of Child Behavior 1954-1957 (Box 53, Folder 30-33)
  - 87 Education 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 34)
  - 88 Adolescence, Adulthood, and Old Age 1954-1956 (Box 53, Folder 35)
  - Survey Schedules 1954-1956 (Box 54, Folder 1)
  - Keys to Rankhandi File Materials 1955, 1965 (Box 54, Folder 2)
  - Interviews, Schedules, etc. Rankhandi 1955 (Box 54, Folder 3)
  - Interview Guides 1955-1956 (Box 54, Folder 4)
  - Questionnaires 1955-1956 (Box 54, Folder 5)
  - Adalat Panchayat Interview Guides Rankhandi 1955 (Box 54, Folder 6)
  - Adult and Social Education Questionnaires (2) I Rankhandi 1955 (Box 54, Folder 7)
  - Agriculture Interview Guide 1956 (Box 54, Folder 8)
  - Artisans Survey Rankhandi 1956 (Box 54, Folder 9)
  - Association and Communications Questionnaire Chuulaa Groups Rankhandi 195- (Box 54, Folder 10)
  - Association and Communications Questionnaire male heads 195- (Box 54, Folder 11)
  - Calendrical Rites Interview Guides Rankhandi 1956 (Box 54, Folder 12)
  - CDP Questionnaires I 1) VLW 2) Felt Needs 3) 1st Reactions 1955 (Box 54, Folder 13)
  - Cornell-Methodology Project Questionnaire India 195- (Box 54, Folder 14)
  - Daily Income and Expenditures Rajput Families 195- (Box 54, Folder 15)
  - Daily Routine Questionnaire (Male) For Bhanghis 1955 (Box 54, Folder 16)
  - Daily Routine Survey Rankhandi 195- (Box 54, Folder 17)
  - Debts Questionnaire for Bhanghis 195- (Box 54, Folder 18)
  - Diet Questionnaire I Rankhandi 1956 (Box 54, Folder 19)
  - Itinerant Merchants Interview Guide 1955 (Box 54, Folder 20)
  - Janamas Tamii Interview Guide Rankhandi I 1955 (Box 54, Folder 21)
  - Kin Groups Interview Guide for Khaandaan I 1955-1956 (Box 54, Folder 22)
  - Labor Questionnaire Jajmani-Lagdaar Rankhandi I 195- (Box 54, Folder 23)
  - Married Daughters of Rankhandi, Married Women Living in Rankhandi (Survey Schedules) 1955-1956 (Box 54, Folder 24)
  - Doll Play and Child Interview Rankhandi 195- (Box 54, Folder 25)
  - Education Questionnaire for Bhanghis 195- (Box 54, Folder 26)
  - Education Questionnaire Rajput Women Rankhandi I 195- (Box 54, Folder 27)
  - Farmer Personality Guide for Bhanghis 195- (Box 54, Folder 28)
  - Farm Survey Rankhandi 195- (Box 54, Folder 29)
  - Food Consumption Questionnaire Rankhandi 195- (Box 54, Folder 30)
  - Glossary of Village Culture Rankhandi I 1956 (Box 54, Folder 31)
  - Gram Panchayat Members Interview Guide Rankhandi I 1955 (Box 54, Folder 32)
  - Holi-Festival Questionnaire for Bhanghis (2 parts) I 195- (Box 54, Folder 33)
  - Hopper, D. W. Input-Output Questionnaire I 1955 (Box 54, Folder 34)
  - House Group Questionnaire Rankhandi I 195- (Box 54, Folder 35)
  - Household Inventory I 1956 (Box 54, Folder 36)
  - Infancy and Childhood Interview Guide Rankhandi 1956 (Box 54, Folder 37)
  - Interview Guide for Outaise Employment for Bhanghis 195- (Box 54, Folder 38)
  - Interview on Animals for Bhanghis I 195- (Box 54, Folder 39)
  - Mother Interview, 1 and 2 Rankhandi I 195- (Box 54, Folder 40)
  - Other Income-Producing Activities of Laagdaars I 1956 (Box 54, Folder 41)
  - Payments of Bhanghis Questionnaire I 195- (Box 54, Folder 42)
  - Personal Property Interview (Women) I 1956 (Box 54, Folder 43)
  - Production and Trade Survey Rankhandi I 1956 (Box 54, Folder 44)
  - Property Questionnaire Rajput Women Rankhandi I 195- (Box 54, Folder 45)
  - Recreation Questionnaire Rajput Women Rankhandi I 195- (Box 54, Folder 46)
  - Record of Inter-Village Visits Questionnaire for Bhanghis 195- (Box 54, Folder 47)
  - Religious Beliefs Questionnaires for Bhanghis 195- (Box 54, Folder 48)
  - Schedule "B" Methodology Project written in Maghi Script I 1955 (Box 54, Folder 49)
  - Social Distance with Casets I 1955 (Box 54, Folder 50)
  - Stock Survey Rankhandi I 1955 (Box 54, Folder 51)
  - Survey of Retail Shops Rankhandi I 195- (Box 54, Folder 52)
  - Survey Schedule for Bhanghis at Holi Rankhandi I 195- (Box 54, Folder 53)
  - Widowhood and Dependency Questionnaire - Rajput Widows Rankhandi I 195- (Box 54, Folder 54)
  - Women and CDP Questionnaire Rankhandi I 1955 (Box 54, Folder 55)
  - Elwyn Lapoint Thesis (Partial Draft) 1971 (Box 54, Folder 56)
  - 84 C.D.S of India (Box 55, Folder 1)
  - Rankhandi Documentary Film B020 2003 (Box 55, Folder 2)
  - VHS-Richter Productions, INC., Prosperity comes to Khalapur (Box 55, Folder 3)